A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of Reports, Office Files of Richard Magat FA728
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of Reports, Office Files of Richard Magat
1961-1982
Rockefeller Archive Center
Magat, Richard
Ford Foundation
FA728
7.6 Cubic Feet
The Office of Reports, Office Files of Richard Magat were transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives with Office of Reports files in at least five separate sections between 1982 and 1986. Because there was no discernible distinction between Mr. Magat's office files and Office of Reports records, the decision was made to define as his office files only those files that were clearly created and maintained by Mr. Magat. Additional "Magat files" are interspersed in Office of Reports records. Mr. Magat also served as Special Assistant to the Mayor's Panel on Decentralization of New York City Schools. In 1979 Mr. Magat donated his Panel papers to the Ford Foundation Archives. These papers are included in this collection (Series IV). The Office Files of Richard Magat cover the years 1961-82 and consist of chronological files, inter-office memoranda, correspondence and some printed material. The files measure 9.25 linear feet.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Separated Materials
Speeches, articles, and staff and consultant reports relating to Ford Foundation activities were removed from Mr. Magat's office files and transferred to the appropriate record group. For each removed item a cross-reference sheet was inserted. Drafts of letters, reports, and press releases were removed except in cases where no final copy could be found or where they differed substantially from the final copy.
Biographical / Historical
Richard Magat was a member of the Ford Foundation staff from 1957 until 1982. Throughout his career at the Foundation Mr. Magat worked in the Office of Reports. He held the following positions:
April 1957, Writer
October 1957, Program Assistant
May 1958, Director
March 1968, Director and Editor
January 1982, Director (part time)
As Director and Editor, Mr. Magat was responsible for: preparing press releases, writing notes to editors and drafting letters to congressmen; writing and editing Foundation publications and articles including the Annual Report, Current Interests, and Ford Foundation Letter; recommending public reports on Foundation activity; responding to media inquiries and arranging press conferences; and administering the Office of Reports.
Mr. Magat also held the following positions:
1947-51, Dayton Daily News, Ohio, The Binghamton Sun, New York, Reporter
1951-52, McGraw-Hill Book Company, Editor in Technical Writing Service
1952-53, Paramount News, Script Writer
1953-57, New York University, Senior News Writer, Office of Information Services
1967, Mayor's Advisory Panel on Decentralization of NYC Schools, Special Assistant
1969, SUNY (Mount Vernon) Cooperative College, Instructor
1975, Joint Committee for the Reappraisal of the Role of the Red Cross, Editor
1979, SUNY (New York) Fashion Institute of Technology, Instructor
Mr. Magat was born January 1, 1927. He received his A.B. degree in 1947 from New York University. Mr. Magat took additional courses at Columbia University, New York University and the New School. Mr. Magat is the author of Ford Foundation at Work, New York: Plenum (1979), and As Others See Us, Geneva: Henry Dumant Institute (1975). He also wrote articles for Saturday Review, Consumer Reports, Trans-action and other magazines and journals. Mr. Magat left the Ford Foundation in September 1982 to become President of the Edward W. Hazen Foundation.
Scope and Contents
The Office Files consist of 9.25 linear feet of correspondence, memoranda, chronological files, and printed material. They document the activities and concerns of Mr. Magat between 1961 and 1982 in his position as Director and Editor of the Office of Reports.
The Office Files of Richard Magat not only reflect the administrative aspects of the Office of Reports but also Mr. Magat's concern for accurate media reporting for Foundation activities and the areas of interest of the Foundation between 1961 and 1982. Some of these areas of interest include: the Patman Committee hearings, the 1969 Tax Reform Act, the Mayor's Panel on Decentralization of NYC Schools, "l'affaire F.O.R.D." [Families Opposing Revolutionary Donations], a proposed communications satellite, and retrenchment at the Foundation. The people with whom Mr. Magat corresponded include: Foundation officers Howard Dressner, Harold Howe II, Mitchell Sviridoff and McGeorge Bundy; literary agent Rick Balkin; press contacts Jeff Birnbaum, Herbert Mitgang and Ted Slate; and individuals at the Council on Foundations, Russell Sage Foundation, Grants Magazine and Foundation News.
Arrangement
It was not possible to reconstruct the original order of the files. Series arrangement is artificial and includes the following four series:
I. Inter-office Memoranda, 1961-1982
II. Chronological Files, 1970-1980
III. Press Files, 1965-1982
IV. Mayor's Panel on Decentralization of NYC
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Inter-office Memoranda, 1961-1982; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Inter-office Memoranda, documents Mr. Magat's administrative duties in the Office of Reports. The memoranda also show some of Mr. Magat's concerns: the potential for conflict of interest by employing journalists as Foundation consultants; "flaps"--controversial issues with which the Foundation was involved; and the relationship between the Ford Foundation and the Ford Motor Company. The series is divided into five subseries: general memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, Howard Dressner, Franklin Thomas, and Brock Brower. There is some duplication between the first subseries and the four others.
  Arrangement
  This series is divided into the following five subseries which are arranged chronologically:
  A. General Inter-office Memoranda, 1961-1982
  B. McGeorge Bundy, 1966-1979
  C. Howard Dressner, 1972-1982
  D. Franklin Thomas, 1979-1982
  E. Brock Brower, 1981-1982
  Within each folder the material is arranged chronologically.
  - General Inter-office Memoranda, 1961-1982; A
    Subseries A, General Inter-office Memoranda, 1961-1982, consists of Richard Magat's outgoing memoranda. The memoranda are addressed to the Office of Reports staff and the other individuals in the Ford Foundation. There is some duplication between this subseries and the following subseries.
    - 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1971 January - July (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1971 August - December (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1972 January - June (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1972 July - October (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1972 November - December (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1973 January - February (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1973 March - April (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1973 May - June (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1973 July - August (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1973 September - October (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1974 January - February (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1974 March - April (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1974 May - June (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 1974 July - August (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - 1974 September - October (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - 1974 November - December (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - 1975 January - February (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 1975 March - April (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - 1975 May - June (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 1975 July - August (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 1975 September - October (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - 1975 November - December (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 1976 January - February (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - 1976 March - April (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - 1976 June - July (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - 1976 August - September (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - 1976 October - December (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - 1977 January - February (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - 1977 March - April (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - 1977 May - June (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - 1977 July - September (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - 1977 October - November (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - 1977 December (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - 1978 January - March (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - 1978 April - July (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - 1978 August - October (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - 1978 November - December (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - 1979 January - March (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - 1979 April - July (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - 1979 August - October (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - 1979 November - December (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - 1980 January - December (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - 1981 January - December (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - 1982 January - December (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - McGeorge Bundy, 1966-1979; B
    Subseries B, McGeorge Bundy, 1966-1979, contains Magat's outgoing memoranda addressed to President Bundy. Also included in this subseries is "Bundy's Out of Town Appearances (1972-1974), itineraries, appointment schedules and arrangements with public relations firms for Bundy's visits to cities.
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1974 January - July (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1974 August - December (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, McGeorge Bundy, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Bundy's Out of Town Appearances, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Bundy's Out of Town Appearances, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Bundy's Out of Town Appearances, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Howard Dressner, 1972-1982; C
    Subseries C, Howard Dressner, 1972-1982, contains Magat's inter-office memoranda addressed to Howard Dressner, Secretary and General Counsel (1971-1984).
    - 1973 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - 1974 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - 1975 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - 1976 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - 1977 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - 1978 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - 1979 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - 1980 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - 1981 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Franklin Thomas, 1979-1982; D
    Subseries D, Franklin Thomas, 1979-1982, contains Magat's inter-office memoranda addressed to Franklin Thomas, President of the Ford Foundation (1979-1996).
    - 1979 (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - 1980 (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - 1981 (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - 1982 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Brock Brower, 1981-1982; E
    Subseries E, Brock Brower, 1981-1982, contains Magat's memoranda addressed to Brock Brower, who served as Advisor to the President and who was responsible for external dissemination of the results of Ford Foundation programs (1981-1983).
    - 1981 (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - 1982 (Box 8, Folder 83)
- Chronological Files, 1970-1980; II
  Series II, Chronological Files, shows Mr. Magat's activities with non-Foundation individuals. This series includes the outgoing correspondence addressed to literary agents, media and publishing contacts, freelance writers, copy editors, and colleagues at other foundations. The series also includes some of Mr. Magat's responses to requests for information from interested individuals and a small amount of incoming correspondence.
  This series is arranged in chronological order. Within each folder the items are in reverse chronological order.
  - 1970 October - December (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - 1971 January - February (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - 1971 March - April (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - 1971 May - June (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - 1971 July - August (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - 1971 September - October (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - 1971 November - December (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - 1972 January - February (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - 1972 March - April (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - 1972 May - June (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - 1972 July - August (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - 1972 September - October (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - 1972 November - December (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - 1973 January - February (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - 1973 March - April (Box 10, Folder 98)
  - 1973 May - June (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - 1973 July - August (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - 1973 September - October (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - 1973 November - December (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - 1974 January - February (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - 1974 March - April (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - 1974 May - June (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - 1974 July - August (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - 1974 September - October (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - 1974 November - December (Box 11, Folder 108)
  - 1975 January - February (Box 11, Folder 109)
  - 1975 March - April (Box 11, Folder 110)
  - 1975 May - June (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - 1975 July - August (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - 1975 September - October (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - 1975 November - December (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - 1976 January - February (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - 1976 March - April (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - 1976 May - June (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - 1976 July - August (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - 1976 September - October (Box 11, Folder 119)
  - 1976 November - December (Box 11, Folder 120)
  - 1977 January - February (Box 11, Folder 121)
  - 1977 March - April (Box 11, Folder 122)
  - 1977 May - June (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - 1977 July - August (Box 11, Folder 124)
  - 1977 September - October (Box 11, Folder 125)
  - 1977 November - December (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - 1978 January - February (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - 1978 March - April (Box 12, Folder 128)
  - 1978 May - June (Box 12, Folder 129)
  - 1978 July - August (Box 12, Folder 130)
  - 1978 September (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - 1978 October (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - 1978 November (Box 12, Folder 133)
  - 1978 December (Box 12, Folder 134)
  - 1979 January (Box 12, Folder 135)
  - 1979 February (Box 12, Folder 136)
  - 1979 March (Box 12, Folder 137)
  - 1979 April (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - 1979 May (Box 13, Folder 139)
  - 1979 June (Box 13, Folder 140)
  - 1979 July (Box 13, Folder 141)
  - 1979 August (Box 13, Folder 142)
  - 1979 September (Box 13, Folder 143)
  - 1979 October (Box 13, Folder 144)
  - 1979 November (Box 13, Folder 145)
  - 1979 December (Box 13, Folder 146)
  - 1980 January (Box 13, Folder 147)
  - 1980 February (Box 13, Folder 148)
  - 1980 March (Box 13, Folder 149)
  - 1980 April (Box 13, Folder 150)
  - 1980 May (Box 14, Folder 151)
  - 1980 June (Box 14, Folder 152)
  - 1980 July (Box 14, Folder 153)
  - 1980 August (Box 14, Folder 154)
  - 1980 September (Box 14, Folder 155)
  - 1980 October (Box 14, Folder 156)
  - 1980 November (Box 14, Folder 157)
  - 1980 December (Box 14, Folder 158)
- Press Files, 1965-1982; III
  Series III, Press Files, demonstrates Mr. Magat's contact with the press: "responding fully to media inquiries.... [and calling] media attention to significant work supported by the Foundation." (Magat to Heard, 1979 Jan. 24, Chronological Files.) The files contain Mr. Magat's outgoing correspondence to his press contacts, often suggesting a story which might be written. The series is divided into two subseries: New York Times press contact files and general press contact files.
  This series is divided into the following two subseries:
  A. New York Times Press Files, 1965-1982 B. General Press Files, 1973-1981 (press contacts except the NYT)
  Both subseries contain Mr. Magat's outgoing correspondence to press contacts. The subseries are arranged in chronological order. Within each folder the material is in reverse chronological order.
  - New York Times Press Files, 1965-1982; A
    - 1965 (Box 15, Folder 159)
    - 1966 (Box 15, Folder 160)
    - 1967 (Box 15, Folder 161)
    - 1968 (Box 15, Folder 162)
    - 1969 (Box 15, Folder 163)
    - 1970 (Box 15, Folder 164)
    - 1971 (Box 15, Folder 165)
    - 1972 (Box 15, Folder 166)
    - 1973 (Box 15, Folder 167)
    - 1974 (Box 15, Folder 168)
    - 1975 (Box 15, Folder 169)
    - 1976 (Box 15, Folder 170)
    - 1977 (Box 15, Folder 171)
    - 1978 (Box 15, Folder 172)
    - 1979 (Box 15, Folder 173)
    - 1980 (Box 15, Folder 174)
    - 1981 (Box 15, Folder 175)
    - 1982 (Box 15, Folder 176)
  - General Press Files, 1973-1981; B
    - 1972 (Box 15, Folder 177)
    - 1973 (Box 15, Folder 178)
    - 1974 (Box 16, Folder 179)
    - 1975 (Box 16, Folder 180)
    - 1976 (Box 16, Folder 181)
    - 1977 (Box 16, Folder 182)
    - 1978 (Box 16, Folder 183)
    - 1979 (Box 16, Folder 184)
    - 1980 (Box 16, Folder 185)
    - 1981 (Box 16, Folder 186)
- Mayor's Panel on Decentralization of NYC Schools, 1961-1969; IV
  Series IV, Mayor's Panel on Decentralization of New York City Schools, contains the materials distributed to the Mayor's Panel for which Mr. Magat served as Special Assistant. The series consists of meeting dockets, reports, correspondence, publications and pamphlets of the Panel for which Magat served as Special Assistant. It is suggested that the researcher use this series in conjunction with the Archives' other holdings on the Mayor's Panel.
  The material in this series was divided by type and arranged chronologically. The list of the original order, "Panel Document File" is in folder 187a of this series.
  - Panel Document File, undated (Box 17, Folder 187a)
  - Meeting Dockets, 1967 May 11 (Box 17, Folder 187)
  - Meeting Dockets, 1967 June 13 (Box 17, Folder 188)
  - Meeting Dockets, 1967 July 12 (Box 17, Folder 189)
  - Meeting Dockets, 1967 July 17 (Box 17, Folder 190)
  - Meeting Dockets, 1967 July 20 (Box 17, Folder 191)
  - Meeting Dockets, 1967 August 3 (Box 17, Folder 192)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, undated (Box 17, Folder 193)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, undated (Box 17, Folder 194)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, undated (Box 17, Folder 195)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, 1961 November 8 (Box 18, Folder 196)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, 1963 June 17 - 1967 February 28 (Box 18, Folder 197)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, 1967 March 1 - May 31 (Box 18, Folder 198)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, 1967 June (Box 18, Folder 199)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, 1967 June 5-30 (Box 18, Folder 200)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, 1967 July 17 - September 5 (Box 18, Folder 201)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, 1967 November 15 (Box 18, Folder 202)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, 1967 December (Box 18, Folder 203)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, 1968 February (Box 18, Folder 204)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, 1968 February 7-March 29 (Box 18, Folder 205)
  - Reports, Proposals, and Statements, 1968 July 30 (Box 19, Folder 206)
  - Correspondence and Press Releases, undated (Box 19, Folder 207)
  - Correspondence and Press Releases, 1963 October 18-25 (Box 19, Folder 208)
  - Correspondence and Press Releases, 1967 February 6-May 15 (Box 19, Folder 209)
  - Correspondence and Press Releases, 1967 June 1-August 22 (Box 19, Folder 210)
  - Correspondence and Press Releases, 1967 September 7 - December 30 (Box 19, Folder 211)
  - Correspondence and Press Releases, 1968 January 8-December 12 (Box 19, Folder 212)
  - Publications and Printed Material
    - Community News Service - "Educating the Young," Tom Brooks (photocopy); "Schools and Politics in the Big City," Robert H. Salisbury (photocopy) (Box 19, Folder 213)
    - Citizens Committee for the Public Schools, Inc. (newsletters), undated (Box 19, Folder 214)
    - "50,000 Teachers Are Standing Up for ... " UFT (leaflet), undated (Box 19, Folder 215)
    - "Decentralization within Urban School Systems," John W. Polley (photocopy); "Telling the School Story is Not Enough," Dr. Fusco, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 216)
    - "The Education of Minority Group Children," Harlem Parents Committee, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 217)
    - "Educational Survey Report for the Philadelphia Board of Public Education", 1965 (Box 19, Folder 218)
    - "Facts and Figures 1966-67," New York City Public Schools (Box 19, Folder 219)
    - "The Living End," Roger Starr (photocopy); National Center for Citizens in Education (newsletter), 1966 (Box 19, Folder 220)
    - "Performance & Promise: New York City's Local School Board Revisited," Women's City Club of New York, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 221)
    - "Governing the Public Schools," Marilyn Gittell (photocopy); "The Issues at I.S. 201: A View From the Parent's Committee," Dorothy C. Jones (photocopy), 1966 (Box 20, Folder 222)
    - "Report on the Merger Issue to the Louisville Public School System and the Jefferson County Public School System", 1966 (Box 20, Folder 223)
    - "Developing New York City's Human Resources," Institute of Public Administration. Vol. I and II., 1966 June (Box 20, Folder 224)
    - "Participants and Participation," Marilyn Gittell, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 225)
    - "A Brief Look from Another Perspective," Mary Lela Sherburne (photocopy); "Morgan Community School Annual Report to the Community", 1967 (Box 20, Folder 226)
    - "Feasibility of Devising New School Districts," CONSAD Research Corporation; "Innovation at Rough Rock," Estelle Fuchs (photocopy); "Know Your Schools Fact Sheet," National Committee for Support of the Public Schools; "No More Nonsense About Ghetto Education," Joseph Alsop; "Population Characteristics," Bureau of Census; "Problems of School Decentralization in NYC," Marilyn Gittell (photocopy), 1967 (Box 20, Folder 227)
    - "Summary of Proposed Programs," 1967-68, Dr. Bernard Donovan (Box 20, Folder 228)
    - Mr. Bundy's Bundle (leaflet); "The Constitutional Right of Negro Freedom Revisited," Arthur Kinoy (photocopy); "CSA Response to the Lindsay-Bundy Proposal" (pamphlet); Citizen Planning (bulletin); "Agenda," Women's City Club of New York; Special Report, National Committee for Support of Public Schools; "Decentralization for What?", Irving Kristol (photocopy); "We are Fighting for All New Yorkers" UFT (leaflet); "The Burden of Blame: A Report...," NYCLU (pamphlet), 1968 (Box 20, Folder 229)
    - "Community Institute for Community Studies" (newsletter); "Community Issues," Institute for Community Studies; "Compact," Education Commission of the States; "Race Relations Reporter," Race Relations Information Center; "New Detroit Now" (newsletter), 1969 (Box 20, Folder 230)
    - Miscellaneous Panel Material, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 231)